Hey there, welcome to the Paws at Data Science Hangout. I'm Libby Herron, and this is a recording
of our weekly community call that happens every Thursday at 12 p.m. U.S. Eastern Time.
If you are not joining us live, you miss out on the amazing chat that's going on. So find
the link in the description where you can add our call to your calendar and come hang
out with the most supportive, friendly, and funny data community you'll ever experience.
Can't wait to see you there.
In celebration of five years of the Hangout, I am so excited to introduce you to our featured
leader today. We are joined by Hubert Hickman, Senior Data Strategist and Data Operations
Lead at the University of Chicago's Data for the Common Good, which is just such a cool
phrase, Data for the Common Good. I love it so much. Hubert, welcome, but not really
welcome because you've been joining the Hangout for so long, and a lot of people know your
face and your name. I would love it if you could introduce yourself, tell us a little
bit about what you do, and something that you like to do for fun.
Thank you, Libby, and all the Paws at folks for this Hangout. It's a great place. I am
Hubert Hickman. As Libby said, I'm the Senior Data Strategist and Data Operations Lead for
Data for the Common Good, also known as D4CG at the University of Chicago. We are the home
of the Pediatric Cancer Data Commons, among other initiatives, but the PCDC, Pediatric
Cancer Data Commons, is a consortia of consortia, 16 different pediatric cancer types, all rolled
into an umbrella, but each with their own data and governance structures, but unified
into the PCDC. The data is not ours. We hold the data. It is governed by the consortia
themselves. Our data dictionaries are open. You can go and look at them. And so there's
a lot of work that goes in within our group to putting those data dictionaries together,
getting the data in, wizardry on governance and agreements and data use agreements and that sort
of stuff. There's also other initiatives like penetrating brain injuries, rare epilepsies,
and other things that are happening. I, by training, I am a very mathy computer scientist.
I am one of those folks who did not complete a PhD. I think there's a number of us here on
the Hangout that are in that state. My early career was industrial wastewater treatment,
college administration, defense and power engineering. And since 1993, I've been working
in clinical and research and dramatics. I got into this area because of a friendship with a
liver transplant surgeon here in Omaha. Eventually, one thing led to another. Because of that
friendship, I co-founded a company with addition of a grad school buddy in my basement dealing
with caring for and transplant patients and helping centers deal with all the logistics
and clinical things that were needed. That company started in my basement, stayed there
for two years. 17 years later, we had 65 transplant sites across the US, Canada, and Australia. And I
think about a third of the transplant patients were in our systems in the US. After the company
sold, in the meantime, in 2003, I worked as an employee at UNMC working on the NICU system,
the new things that led to a successful system. In 2012, the EPIC came in, our team was no longer
needed for some of the charting for the physician documentation system at UNMC. And so I sort of
rattled around a little bit after the company sold with that, got into the research informatics side
from a call from another doctor, a different doctor at UNMC that wanted help setting up a
coordinate node at UNMC, Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Network, one of the national research
networks. And so that got me into the research side, ITV2, the research data warehouse. That
led in 2015 to another company finding me that did the same sort of work at NYU Langone, ITV2
primarily in research data. That led, another step led to some initial work with the National
Cancer Institute in 2017. That project was called DI3, integrating imagery, image data,
multimodal image data, along with research study data. That's the first time I'd actually
heard of the Chicago group as I knew it as then because they were also one of the other groups
working on this project. That project took ITV2, research study data, integrated that,
that's also where I ran into R because I needed a thing that could write SAS export files for
SDTM, study data tabulation model files, and I need a little web server to write extensions for
what, for ITV2. And I found this thing called R and Shiny and then, hmm, this will fill the bill,
and it did. That led to more work with the National Cancer Institute within the clinical
trial reporting program, dealing with structuring of unstructured clinical trial inclusion and
exclusion criteria and trial search space. That was my primary focus for the time at NCI. And in
early 2024, I moved to the D4CG group. It is a, you know, it is a wonderful group of folks. We're
doing really great work in areas where that work is really needed. I think I've written code in
16 different programming languages over the years. I counted them up, and I keep thinking good ones
every now and then. I will, yeah, I will say this. I have been very fortunate in my career that I,
you know, I have made a difference and done good work. And, you know, there's a combination of
factors that led to that, but. Well, there's a couple of things I heard in there that I would
love to, like, pick back up and just ask you some more questions about. One is you said you didn't
complete a PhD, which I think that a lot of people can relate to, and that you came from a more
software engineer mathy background. So you've come to data science from, like, the side, right? Not
from, straight up from statistics. And the other one is that you did not have a background in
cancer research. You got here because you made a friend, right? You sort of found somebody who
pulled you in to help you solve a problem. And you said yes to, sure, I'll help you solve this
problem that I know nothing about. So could you tell me a little bit about how you met that friend?
Did you join a community like this one? What did that look like?
We, in 1990, bought a computer called the Next Workstation. If you remember what Steve Jobs did
between getting fired from Apple and getting rehired to Apple, he did Next. And it was a
wonderful system, especially compared to the state-of-the-art of today. It had lots of power,
a wonderful GUI, networking. It was Unix underneath. So it was, for me, it was like,
oh, that's my dream computer. And this transplant surgeon, unbeknownst to me, had bought one of
these machines too. And I had set up a little user group, and I think there were like five of us in
Omaha. It was not a big community. And that's how I met him. And they had had IBM Enterprise
Alliance come in to make a smoke and mirrors demo system for them. So they had had two different
unsuccessful runs at building a system to meet their needs. And when we said, yes, oh, yeah,
we can do this, we were very naive. We said, oh, look. You didn't have a company at that point,
right? You were just like, I think we can tackle this problem to help you manage these transplant
patients. Right. And we said, oh, three months. It took us two years to build that system out.
So there was a lot of learning and deep learning. There was no clinical background in my history,
but you have to learn and listen and watch how people work, what the needs were,
and juggle all the other things to make a go of it. And so, yeah, it was a challenge.
But fortunately, my friend was a very patient man. So.
So you've been building data solutions for many, many years. I'm wondering what advice you would
give somebody who is coming in new to the game and is being tasked with building a data solution
for somebody? Because my advice is always go sit with them, shadow them, watch them work for a
really long time and ask them a bunch of questions. How long did you spend just watching the way that
people were interacting with their existing solution for those patients?
Oh, a very long time. I mean, we did interviews upon interviews, watched them work. I made cassette
tapes back in the day of all these so I could replay them because I didn't know. It's like
I give the analogy of Homer's dog and the Simpsons spot, you know, spot doesn't understand any word
other than his name. You know, so it's like blah, blah, blah, spot, blah, blah, blah, spot.
So that's the way I felt at first. So you have to be able, I think, to be successful in some
of these arenas to where there's sort of this deep domain knowledge needed. You have to be able to
learn that domain well enough and step back and make a solution, you know, see what the real
problems are. Because that's it's not necessarily the problems they're telling you what's in front
of them, but what are the patterns? Where are they inefficient? What do they need to see? And
that's whether it's clinical or research, you know, some of those same questions apply. You've
got to learn and be willing to learn enough of the domain to know what a system might offer
in terms of solving real problems for people, be it research or clinical workflows.
Yeah, I wanted to call out something that Abigail just said in the chat,
and then I'm going to read Abigail's question in the Slido. By the way, you can ask questions in
the Slido, everybody, don't forget. Because Abigail said these days that she does a lot more
just build the thing and put it in front of somebody now because the building part has gotten
so much faster and then people can respond to it. I'm wondering if you have seen AI-driven
development sort of shift that building bespoke stuff game a little bit.
It has. And that's, you know, AI is an accelerant for good or for evil or for bad things. You know,
you can use it in a good way and a bad way. And the bad way, the good way, excuse me,
the good way is just what Abigail mentioned, that it makes putting a prototype together
really easy. One of the things I'm working on now in D4CG is, you know, we're working on
direct from patient data via FHIR and research data. And, you know, some of that data is ugly.
And, you know, the EHR data is all over the place and things are here, things are there.
It's not a straightforward or easy issue to solve. But once you get the data part of this figured out,
you know, what the data should look like, what's the shape, what's the structure of the data,
and I still think you need to have a model of that in your head, at least, of what this data,
what the data are all about. You know, you can literally, I mean, what I did for one of my,
one of my current projects is the first version of this. I just drew pictures for Claude and said,
here's the data, here's what I want you to do. And it did a really bad first version of that.
Yeah, it wasn't very good at all. But it put it in front of my face to see it. And then you can
realize, oh, this is not so good. But then you can go and start cycling and iterating that to
make it better. And then you put it in front of people now, oh, wow, this is nice. And so,
that thing that would have taken me months and months and months and months and months to write,
if I had to do it myself, Claude's perfectly happy doing crazy JavaScript stuff and wiring
in shiny reactives and whatnot to make things work. And it's perfectly, you know, it does a
good job. Now, you still have to ultimately go and write a lot of LLM code and sort of de-slop it
once you're all done with it. De-slopping, how unfortunate. It's true. Okay, well, Abigail's
question was about programming languages, because you mentioned that you work in 16 programming
languages. And I just asked you about AI, which means that you have seen a lot of evolution over
the years and a lot of change in technology, and you've had to navigate all of that. Hats off to
you, because it's hard for me, and I only know a handful of programming languages, and not very
well. So, Abigail's question was, what was your favorite programming language and your least
favorite programming languages and why? And are there any that you wish you could still work in
that maybe you don't get to work in anymore? Oh, that's a good question. Least favorite?
I would... I'm going to say I do not like working in Java. I've worked in it, but it's just not my
favorite. It seems wordy, and I know lots of people love it, and it's efficient. They work in it day
on, day out, but it's just not my cup of tea. I'm not a big Java fan. Favorites depends upon the
time you ask. I've had many favorites over the years, but mainly those which allow me to get
my work done without getting in the way, and I like Python. Both Python and R for that. I do
most of the GUI work I do in R. It just makes... I know how Shiny works. The way reactives and
interactivity work is straightforward enough that you can get what you need done without requiring
lots and lots and lots of work. In Python, I first ran across that in 2001 or so, back in 1.5 Python
days, and I could just almost think Python when you started writing Python. And when we did the
system in 2003 at UNMC, that was written in Python, and that was not a popular choice at the time. I
had lots of people wander by my office, wander by my office, and they'd say, oh, I'm going to
be writing this in .NET or Java or whatever. But it's like, nope, we're going to do it this way.
Now Python runs most of the world, but yeah, those are my answers. And other languages I've
certainly enjoyed. You don't stay in it. Some of those languages are dead now. Some are still
around. But I think Python and R are my favorites. Java.
Some will never die.
Some will never die. Perl, I can write fine, but you can't read it later.
Someone said in the chat, Pauline said, I enjoy writing in Perl, and I miss that.
The one I was thinking about was COBOL, that just it never dies, because there's so much
that's written in COBOL that needs to survive for business purposes. I feel like every
business that's been around for at least 50 years needs to have at least one COBOL person.
At least that's in my experience. Well, Arsenis, I saw you piggybacked
on to Abigail's question. Would you like to ask that one live?
Before I close Abigail's question. All right. Awesome.
Sure. Thanks. So about programming languages still, is there one or a couple, and I think
you just mentioned R and Python, but are they the ones that you prefer for data science
more specifically versus other software engineering tasks and things of that nature?
Yeah, I think for the data science-y part, I think R. You can do it in R and Python.
A lot of people doing Python. My own preferences are just because it's a little more concise
and data frames kind of work consistently within the ecosystem. But it's the conciseness of it all,
and plus just the wide range of things that are available. Whatever you need, there's a library
for that probably in data science. And I think Python may have caught up a lot of that way,
but my personal use of Python is sort of the backend use case, data processing,
that versus, okay, let's do presentation. I did one of the apps that I've written for PCDC.
It is for the PCDC, but DC4G is a pivot table app, which uses the Chinese JavaScript pivot table,
the drag and drop pivot table widget. Then it's an internal app, but it's a good example. Okay,
I use Python to manipulate the data coming out to get it into the structure I needed. But
yeah, pivot table, all this other stuff, you can see heat maps, graphs, this, that,
all the other things. That was not much code to get a lot of functionality out of things,
but I would say R. And I think in terms of what people are learning these days, folks coming out
of college, I think R is more and more popular for the data science community as well. Because
it's open, you can go get it, like SAS or some of the other things that cost money, or you get
some version that's not really for commercial use or something. I love it. Very good answer.
Thank you so much for asking that piggyback question. And thank you, Abigail, for asking
your original question as well. And we have so many questions popping up in the Slido now. Thank
you, everybody. I would love it if we could ask Natasha's question really quickly, which is one
of my favorites. She always asks, what does an average day look like for you? Or maybe an average
week, if every day is not the same? Yeah, I think a lot of what I do on a day-to-day basis,
within an average week, I rotate. I work with the data standards group, developers group,
I work in their research group. So there's many different groups that are very internal,
that I sort of float between and in. And so there's what I would call standard sort of,
I need to get this code written to do these things. And I've got features that need to go
into an app I'm working on, or there's some backend thing, or I need to update one of the
things that's one of the apps that I support. So there's that part of the aspect. The other part
of it is being in what were the kinds of things we should be doing at a higher level in the group,
just participating in that, throwing out research ideas and everything, and thinking about what
things should come, how, what are out there in terms of opportunities for us to do things,
throwing ideas out on the table. And not all of Hubert's ideas are great, but I'm going to throw
them out on the table to say, well, what about this idea or that idea, and pull things together.
And to support other sort of group questions that may come my way, or someone asks, well,
what do you think about this, that? So it's a mix of things. I'm not a always software developer,
or data, always data person, or always other person. So it's a mix of different things
that I do during the course of a week. And the days do, you know,
no days alike in my week because of meetings and other things.
I think that it's really hard for me to even, even say, average week, because throughout the
year, things change so much, right? And if you work in a project based environment,
and a client based environment, things change constantly. I don't know if anybody else can
relate. I'm seeing some nodding heads. Yes. Okay, I feel better. I was just thinking how
PositConf is actually coming up in September, and how that has changed the focus, my focus over,
you know, increasingly over the past few weeks. And as we get closer to September,
we'll be like super, super focused on PositConf for a while.
I'm seeing some great chatter in the chat, by the way, about math. If you are a math person,
Abigail Haddad had mentioned like, hey, if you want to shout out to me math people about
combinatorials and stuff like that. So somebody go find and, and relate in the chat and hook up
there. Okay. So let's hop back over to the Slido where I would love it if Mike could unmute and ask
his question live. Mike K. Smith. I will highlight it and I'll also put it in the chat. Hey, Mike.
So thanks, Hubert. My, my question was kind of the, do you, what differences would you
think of or see between developing tools for like a startup or a for profit organization versus
developing things as you're doing for public good? Does that change how you think about,
you know, who the customer is or what the focus of the product is?
It does. You know, when you're working in some sort of academic medical area or academic research
area, the focus is not really a product focus. So it's more like, you know, how do we get this
research data? There's plenty of things to go tackle and pulling research data together.
How do we present it? Not just the sort of statistical analysis to where my statistics
are rusty, very rusty after all these years. But there's that aspect of it, but it's still,
you know, you do have customers. They're just not like outside paying, you know, paying customers.
So you still have to pay attention to what the needs are and where you may make it better. If
you're in a small commercial organization, then, then it's a different game in terms of what do
we need to do to bring in revenue? What do we have to do? But a small organization is also
different than a large organization. And it's, you know, large organizations, some of them are,
you know, there's lots of consultancies and this and that, where you design a project and then
you're part of the big team and you're fully agile of all the pageantry. And so sometimes you
as an individual don't have much leeway in how things get done. You, you know, sometimes you,
you know, I think some of the larger development efforts, you lose the plot because of things like
agile. And, you know, you have so many people in there, they're not very near the customers,
not very near, whether it be researchers or clinicians or whomever it may be, they're not,
they're not very close to that customer. And so the further away you are from the people you're
building software tools for, whether it's like, you know, a tool like the PCDC, we're very close
to those, to those folks who are contributing the data and managing the data and, and handing data
to us. So the more distance you get between you and the people who lay hands on your software,
then things, I think, tend to unravel. And I think we see that in how much of software is
the, it's so bloated and just, you know, it's, it's, you know, the people who are writing it
aren't really, you know, that invested sometimes to make it work right. I mean,
I've been physically threatened by a transplant surgeon one time if the software didn't work
right. So, you know, sometimes it's a little bit too close to some of those customers, but,
you know, there, there is being bought into it. And you've got to have some, the other thing to
this, if you're close to those people and you, you have some passion for making sure that your
software does the right thing, to where if you're in a big organization, you know, they're 30 steps
away. I'm just marking off tickets and here we go. And if it's clunky, they'll use it anyway.
But that's, that's not an environment I could live in for very long.
I wouldn't want people to use clunky things either.
Well, I have a fantastic question from Rowan now, but I see an asterisk. So I'm going to ask that
question for Rowan and I'm going to put it in the chat as well. And it says, what was your biggest
struggle starting a company? Cause it sounds like the clientele was kind of baked into your
motivation to start. So what struggles did you run into outside of that? What a great question.
Cause often like finding your clientele is the big thing people stop on where they're like,
Oh no, I'm now sales and marketing. And I have to figure this out. What were some of the things
you struggled with? Oh God, everything at first. All the things really. And we didn't, we didn't
know anything about business. We were soft computer scientists. We, we knew about how to build
software, but not much else. So there was a lot of sort of hard learning until we got a few
customers and actually started bringing in revenue to initially where the company started doing okay.
After that, that took a while. It's not easy doing the things that we had to do, but even early on
our demos of software showed us that product wise, we were on the right track. Cause we
are very good. You know, people loved what they would see in our software and for what it could
do and funding, how to get to the contracts, how to do maintenance contracts, how to charge for
things, you know, how to price things, all those things. And eventually, you know, we were
fortunate enough to get through all of that. Was the solution just trying things that didn't
work and learning from them, or was it also going and talking to people, people who had done it
before making friends? We did not have much of that entrepreneurial community back in the early
nineties. I mean, there wasn't the whole startup culture. It wasn't as widespread back then as it
is now. You know, now there's communities, you can find people, it's easier to find people who can
give you advice and help. And it was not, you know, and maybe we just didn't look hard enough
for them, but it was a lot of bootstrapping and learning things through the school of art and
to get there. But we did have that clientele and it's, you know, the organ transplant world was a
small world. You know, I think there were 300 and some odd centers in the U.S. at the time.
So we, you know, we sort of knew what the customer base, what the customer base was.
And that was transplant centers, right? Okay, fantastic. Well, Rowan, thank you for asking that
question. I enjoy hearing about the struggles and the realness. And it is easier to find people
nowadays, but still the feedback that I get from so many people is that the talking to people part
is the hardest part of their job. They're like, I could make tools and solutions all day long,
but I don't know how to reach out to people. I don't know how to talk to people. I don't know
how to get in the same room as them or be listened to. And it is hard. So I feel like the options are
more plentiful now, but it's still, it's still hard. Okay. So we had a question here
that I wanted to shout out to the community at large that I saw in Slido because I saw Zach
shouted out that he had wanted to reply to it in Slido, but the reply button wasn't working.
I'm sorry. They should be working. The reply button should be working. And that is any
introduction to our classes or resources that people would recommend to someone who is just
starting out. So Hubert, I will give this to you as well, if you have any suggestions, but everybody
in the chat, please, please, please shout out any resources that you used when you were getting
started and share them here. I will put this question in the chat. We can sort of thread there.
I know that Zach had said R for data science, which is free and very accessible. There are
all kinds of options. Hubert, do you have anything extra special that you feel like helped you when
you were getting started with R? Yeah, I was just digging, looked at my bookshelf to see what did
I get? I got a few books for R, but I don't remember. I did the, I've got the R cookbook
and R for data science, a version of that. But I just, I just jumped right in. I mean, it's
to me, it was, okay, I've got another language. It's a little different because it's data frame
centric and let me get my brain around that. And so others will probably have more,
more definitive answers than me, but I did R for data science. And I think I've got,
there's another text processing and R something that there's a book, Julia.
I have three R books in my library, only three. So I didn't have a whole lot,
did not have a whole lot of, it didn't take any class or anything. I just jumped in.
Just jumped in. I feel like my advice is do what is going to be right for you based on what you
know about yourself. So if you are a person who is like, I'm a self learner, I'm going to figure
this out on my own. I'm going to hop in. I'm going to go look at repos. I'm going to figure out code,
go for it. If you're a person who is like, I need a class, I need a teacher. I need a classroom of
other students around me. Go find that. Also Posit has Posit Academy, which is open learning
for some of the different tools that you can learn. There are so many different places where
you can find communities of learners like DSLC, data science learning community, which used to
be called R for DS. There's a whole Slack channel. Hopefully somebody can pop the DSLC Slack channel
and join in the Zoom chat for me. That is a great option as well. Okay. Thank you so much
for asking that question, anonymous asker. And I'm so sorry that the reply button might not be
working well in Slido. Let's go back over to Slido here and do, I would like to pull Arsenis in just
one more time. I know you had a piggyback question before, but you have an actual real full question
in Slido. If you would like to ask that live, that'd be great. Yeah, sure. Thanks, Libby. My
first time ever getting, going twice. Anyway, so this one's a little bit different. This question,
it's about some of the problems. So you mentioned that the way you got into kind of the cancer
research and things of that nature was through helping a friend, helping someone solve a problem.
And I'm wondering what types of problems in cancer research presently most piqued your
curiosity from a math stats perspective, and how do you think about approaching them with data? Is
it like modeling, descriptive analysis, that kind of thing? So yeah, that's the question. Thanks.
Yeah. And I'll give a non-math statsy answer to it because I'm really not a stats person
these days. But the problems that I think, you know, there's lots of hard problems in cancer.
There's lots of...
problems and cancer. There's lots of great progress that have been in
different questions. The pediatric cancer area
Dr. Sam Volchenbaum, Director, Center for Pediatric Cancer Research, Center for Pediatric
Cancer Research, Center for Pediatric Cancer Research, Center for Pediatric Cancer Research,
but it's AI will not cure pediatric cancer, but it can help those who can. So part of that is,
if you look at the promise of AI and other things that are out there to help not just AI,
sort of other machine learning sort of environments, modeling, you know, the kinds of things you have,
the data needs can be large. And one of the challenges in our area of pediatric cancer,
in particular, is all these cancers are rare. You're in the rare disease space. And so there's,
for some of these types of diseases, there's just not much data that exists, you know. So
you're not going to have, somebody's not going to build a gigantic LLM to ingest just pediatric
cancer stuff because there's not that many patients with these disease states compared to,
let's say, diabetes or even organ transplantation or other. So the lack of data is a challenge and
how do you address that? And how do you make tools that work in this rare disease space?
That's a big challenge and that's not a stats challenge or other thing. It's just,
I think the biggest challenge is just bringing the data together, like what PCDC does,
but then just working with data where the populations are not going to be large and
making conclusions and the statisticians and others can make their judgments. But knowing
that the set size, you're not going to have a whole lot of data to work with compared to
other diseases where you can sort of wave a wand and get a large population of patients.
Did I answer that? I don't know. I think that that was pretty good. I think that doing novel
things is actually like one of the things that we all talk about LLMs not being super great at,
like if it's been done before and all this training data. So I would love it if other
people in the chat could talk about some novel things that they find LLMs not good at, that they
still really, really need human brains around because I can think of so many.
Okay. Let's hop back over to Slido. Thank you for asking that question. That was fantastic.
Also, I forgot to shout out ISLR, which is my favorite learning R book in the statistics realm,
if you are learning statistics and R at the same time, Introduction to Statistical Learning. It's
just amazing. Okay. We had an anonymous question in the Slido, I believe, and it sort of brings in
a question that I wanted to ask as well. It says, is there an infrastructure you use when
working with collaborative multicenter data without actually sharing the data, for example,
Data Shield or other way for federated data? And I like this question a lot because it brings up a
very specific point that I'm not sure if you expanded on yet, which was that a lot of what
you are doing is bringing in data from a whole bunch of different places, labs, research groups,
things like that, harmonizing it, making it all work together so that everybody can use it, right?
Do you have a specific infrastructure that you use for that collaborative data sharing modeling?
Within PCDC, or within D4CG, because some of this infrastructure is not just PCDC,
there is a data standards team that models what our data model should be, and not every cancer
is going to be looking at the same data. Now, the model we use, the data is submitted to us
at a line level, but we don't have access to their systems. So, we don't know, we're not
logged into their REDCap or EPIC or whatever to get their data. So, the data, we have it,
we don't own it. And then, our group, based on the data modeling, there's a lot of sign-offs
and other things. There's a lot of logistical infrastructure that's built out in the PCDC
for the approval of the data models, of getting the data ingested to bring it into the PCDC.
And then, once you go query the PCDC, there is a governance structure that says,
does your data request get granted or not? And those are generally the executive committees
within the individual disease groups, they make those sorts of decisions like,
yes, D4CG group, you can release this data for this data request for this group. We've deemed it
proper and valid and everything like that. So, we're taking the data in, we present it
for querying purposes, but it's de-identified, you get down, there's a minimum set size,
the typical 10 or something you can go query it. In other models, like if you look at PCORnet,
or trying, there's other national distributed network models to where the data is federated.
So, the data lives at the host site and the queries come in a distributed basis from all
these places that are asking questions. So, you can run a query from one of the client sites
and get generally like obfuscated counts or something back, you know, sites A, B, C, D, E,
that are in this federated network. Here's your stats, here's how many patients meet this criteria
that you put out. And they can do data requests and some places have enclaves set up to do it.
We're looking at enclaves within PCDC, so that there's sort of a space internally that someone
can have a secure workspace to use this data if they don't want to, you know, have to download it
and perform their analysis locally. So, the federated model is one of the models,
especially in some of the larger networks, trying PCORnet, others, where it is this sort of
federated model to do this, to do this kind of work. And there's structures there as well,
there's shared IRBs, there's, you know, there's how do you get approval to get the data and
there's always a process to go through with IRB. Is an IRB a review board? It is an institutional
review board. So, you've got to get an IRB approval to do a research study and generally, you know,
you need, you know, in our case, executive committees serve as a, you know, will the
data be released to that. In other places, locally at a site, a data request would come
into a system and you would still have to have an IRB to release the data for use. And if the IRB
was not specific enough or didn't talk about the data you're asking for,
you've got to go back and revise things. Sometimes the answer was no, not now, you need to
go back and go through your IRB to get this data approved because it's not what you said you wanted.
This sounds like a much more complicated situation than I've ever had to deal with.
It's a lot. Gonzalo in the chat was saying, I'm working with DBT and Looker,
we're both have permissions for who is able to access the data mesh. That is about as complicated
as I feel like I've had to deal with, right? Where like there's data governance that's just
like built into something for me. So, these institutional reviews sound like they're so
far above anything I've had to deal with. It's so complicated. I think that communication becomes
an even more important part of your job at this point. Well, I wanted to define some things for
people. I defined them in the chat, but we heard Hubert saying PCDC a lot and DC4G. So, DC4G is
Data for the Common Good. That's the group that Hubert is working in. And then PCDC is Pediatric
Cancer Data Commons. So, that is that bringing together of data, just in case anybody needed
an out loud explanation of that one. Okay. So, I wanted to, we have 10 minutes left
and we have a unique situation where we have a family member who's a part of our data community
who is on this call because Hubert's daughter, Ruby, is here. And Ruby gave us a little tip
to ask you a specific question. We want Ruby to ask. So, Ruby, if you're willing to unmute and ask
live, I will hand it over. Hey, Ruby. Yes. Hello. It's now family reunion, I guess.
So, not only does my dad, like for his job, do data science for the common good, but also in
his free time, he likes to do sort of data science and software engineering for the common good.
So, I was wondering if you would like to share at all about your side projects, specifically
your like ham radio, ham clock launcher. Just like in your total free time, you're doing this like
open source side project. Yes. Thank you, Dr. Ruby Hickman.
And yes, Ruby is one of my kids and has been a member of the Hangout who
you know, attends every now and then. So, yes, it is a and I will say I'm very proud of Ruby.
Ruby just got her Ph.D. from Harvard. So, and what's your Ph.D. in, Ruby? Then I'll answer
the question. Heck, yeah. A round of applause for Ruby. There's a full round of applause
happening in Zoom. I don't even need to say this. Congratulations, Ruby. That's amazing.
And can I just say the phrase ham clock launcher has me thinking of Rube Goldberg machines
and all kinds of Honey, I Shrunk the Kids inventions. So, can you please explain what a
ham clock is? Yes. So, ham clock, you know, I'm an amateur radio person. Ham clock is a tool that
shows different atmospheric conditions, you know, sunspots, different, there's all kinds of
atmospheric measures about how signal propagation will occur. It is a tool that's been around a
long time. It's kind of clunky to compile and get going on a Mac. So, I made a native wrapper for
this. I made a WX Python app that wraps this, you know, gets and builds everything you need
so you don't have to have developer tools or Mac ports or all the other things that you may need on
a Mac to develop. So, after you just take this wrapper that I built for it, it includes all the
binaries and everything. It's assigned, you know, signed with a developer certificate, goes to the
Apple notary. And there was a video, it got out and video, I think, one of the main video was
viewed like 7,300 times on YouTube or something and probably more now. So, I have several hundred
users for it and it's fun. It's a thing I do that people enjoy using. I know they use it because
if I break an update, they let me know you broke something. Why is it not working? What a privilege
to have users and for them to let you know something is wrong. Amazing. Okay. Wait. I put a
visualization in the chat. I told Hubert not to look at the chat because the chat is going to
be distracting. But I'm hoping that that is helpful with sort of like atmospheric conditions
and like a 24-hour clock up there and what looks like a picture of the sun. But I think that's
earth. Okay. This is hilarious. Ruby, thank you so much for bringing this up. The hilarious part
to me is just the phrase ham clock. I can't stop thinking about it. But this is so much fun.
Everybody go Google ham clock stuff and learn more about it because this is fascinating.
Yeah. If you just Google Google ham clock launcher for the Mac, you will. Anyways.
Ruby shared it too in the chat. Oh, Ruby shared it in the chat. Okay. She's on. It's there.
All right. Thank you, Ruby. Yes. Thank you, Ruby. And Matt says it is the sun. Solar activity
affects radio propagation. Thank you. I'm glad I wasn't wrong. Then that was the sun.
I was thinking, well, maybe it's a, you know, infrared image of something else. I don't know.
Well, we have about five minutes left. That means we have enough time to ask you the question we
love to ask here, which is, do you have a piece of career advice for us? Something that you wish
that you had been told or something that you have just found helpful for you over your career?
Hopefully I'm not putting you on the spot too much. I would think to,
you know, the world is a place, you know, we, there's a lot of peril and promise in the world.
And there's always been a lot of peril and promise in the world. It's different levels
of it now. I think my career advice is, you know, learn that durable domain knowledge in your domain
to, because we can make AI applications to do anything, but if you don't know what it's doing,
because you only have a vague idea of what it's supposed to be doing, then that's an issue. And
so you end up with a lot of these AI slop things that developers, oh yeah, I've coded this and
six hours. Well, yeah, but what does it actually do? And can you explain,
explain it and fix it later when it breaks? So I would say develop that love of learning the
durable domain knowledge, be willing to change. I mean, my 16 programming languages or whatever it
is, you've got to be able, because the world will, you know, things do change all the time.
Five years ago, where was AI? Nowhere. I was just going to say, what is durable these days,
right? Like, what does that even mean? What, it feels like nothing stays. Well, the technology
part is not as durable as it used to be. Things like R and Python and baseline functionality,
those are going to be there, but the libraries will come, some of the libraries may come and go,
but, you know, learning how to solve problems and think deeply. I take a lot of walks where I'm not
listening to podcasts. I'm not listening to music. I just take a walk to help figure things out and
make my, you know, make the brain work. So I think if you can make yourself, it's hard these days,
make yourself take that sort of, I'm not actively doing anything, but these problems are still
percolating in my brain. You know, there's a lot that could come of that, just taking a walk and
just being, and then coming back and taking a look at it. But I would say the deep learning
aspects of it is, you've got to be able to learn. There's still transplant patients that need to be
taken care of. There's still pediatric cancer patients that need help, and we need to develop
new, you know, either regimens for them, new drugs, new combinations of things, new therapies,
new this, new that, new things for the clinicians and the people who are providing the
care for the patients. So there's a lot of problems yet to be solved, but you can't
solve those if you don't understand what it is you're trying to do. And that's what kept me in
this for so long. I enjoy solving those problems, and having seen my software make a difference in
those, but it doesn't matter what area. I'm medical, but that could be in fraud or advertising and
whatever. You have to know, you've got to know that domain. I love that. And I saw so many people
chiming in in the chat with what their thoughts about Durable was, and a lot of them are
soft skill stuff, too. Absolutely. I wish I could get to more of these questions. They're so good.
Yeah. I know. No, the soft skill thing is important. You've got to be able to
listen to people and talk to people, but not assume you know all the answers, because we never do.
That's what I'm taking away from this meeting with you, Hubert, is one, you got into cancer
research by joining a community and making buddies sideways, and two, that staying close to the problem
and building empathy around users and the people who are experiencing the problem can take you
really, really far. There's a great question in Slido about this as well. They said that it was
really motivating and comforting to hear you talk about staying close to the patient, the participant,
the customer as the reason for doing the work and not just a source of data. And they had some
questions. I'll send Hubert all of these unanswered questions so he can see them.
Thank you so much, Hubert. I hope that you had a fantastic time. Thank you so much for joining us
as a featured leader. When you normally join as an attendee, this was wonderful getting to know you
better. Thank you all. I enjoyed this. This was fun. Absolutely. Thank you, Ruby, for making this
a family affair. This was really fun. And thank you to all of you for five years of an amazing
community. If you are not on the Discord, go join the Discord. Hang out with us on the Discord. I
can't wait to see you. We will have a whole week of Discord fun coming up during the PositConf
stuff happening in September, but it's a great place to be. Otherwise, you can continue a lot
of the connections that you made today. If you want to save the chat, three dots in the top of
the chat. If you were in the Zoom app, if you were in the browser, it might be at the bottom.
Help you hold on to some of those resources that people joined and added today in the chat.
Isabella added a quick little download to the chat, which is amazing. Thank you so much,
everybody. We love you so much. Have a fantastic week. While we're saying thank you to everyone
and thank you for five years, I also just want to make sure we say thank you to our behind the scenes
crew of the Hangout here. Heck yeah. Isabella does such an amazing job behind the scenes making
sure everything runs smoothly and sharing all the links and everything. You were so much faster than
me at that. She's faster than all of us. Also, thank you so much to our security team as well
who joined us in the Hangout to make sure that this remains the welcoming and safe space that it
is. Thank you, Diego, for being on today too. Really appreciate it. Thank you, Diego. Sometimes
Chris is here. I know he's not here right now, but thank you, Chris. All right, everybody,
we have to say goodbye, but we'll see you on Tuesday at the Data Science Lab if you want to
join us. I think we're being joined by Emil who is doing themes, quarto slide themes. Anything
with Emil is so much fun. You should join no matter what. She's so fast. She just put it in the
chat. All right, everybody. It's so wonderful to see you. We will see you again next week. Bye.